Guide to the Investigation Files of the Rapp-Coudert Committee TAM.533
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Investigation Files of the Rapp-Coudert Committee (New York State Legislature)
1919-1953
1939-1942
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York (State). Legislature. Joint Legislative Committee to Investigate the Educational System of the State of New York
New York State Archives
TAM.533
7.25 Linear Feet in 57 reels
The Rapp-Coudert Committee (New York State Joint Legislative Committee on the State Education System) was charged with investigating individuals and organizations with suspected radical ties in New York City public schools and colleges from 1940-1942. This collection consists of the Committee's investigation files including correspondence, interview notes, lists and hearing transcripts; minutes; and copies of Communist, anti-war and civil liberties publications collected by the Committee in the course of investigations. Many files contain extensive notes on individuals under investigation, and include documentation on other persons suspected of ties to Communism. (Note that Tamiment Library holds only a microfilm version of this collection - Film R-7860. The original documents are held by the New York State Archives.)
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were loaned by the New York State Archives in 2009 for the purpose of producing a microfilm copy to add to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive's permanent collection. The accession number associated with this collection is 2010.032
Arrangement
The New York State Archives retained the original Case Number order established by the Rapp-Coudert Committee.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Joint Legislative Committee of the State Education System, chaired by Assemblyman Herbert A. Rapp, was created by concurrent resolution of the New York State Senate and Assembly on March 29, 1940. The Committee was given broad authority to investigate the administration and financing of education in the state, and to study "the extent, if any, to which subversive activities may have been permitted to exist in the schools and colleges of the public educational system of the City of New York" (1942 report). Because of the wide scope of its charge, a special subcommittee, chaired by Senator Frederick R. Coudert, was assigned to investigate whether left- and/or right-wing movements -- Communism, Fascism and Nazism -- had penetrated New York City public schools and colleges.
By the conclusion of its investigation, the "Rapp-Coudert Committee" had interviewed almost 700 people and interrogated some 500 witnesses in a series of open and closed hearings on the extent of "subversive activities" in New York City education, resulting in the removal of teachers, professors, and college administrators from their positions. At the City College of New York, the Rapp-Coudert investigations resulted in the termination of over fifty faculty and staff, including Professor Jack Foner, a historian who was accused of injecting left-wing thought into the classroom and devoting excessive attention to the importance of African Americans in the curriculum.
According to its final report, the Rapp-Coudert Committee found no significant body of evidence showing a Nazi or Fascist "conspiracy against the schools," but it did uncover substantial evidence on the part of the Communist Party to penetrate into the public school and higher education systems. In particular, the Committee identifed three organizations -- the Teachers Union, College Teachers Union and American Student Union -- through which the Communist Party was supposedly working (1942 report). The Rapp-Coudert Committee was disbanded in 1942, even though the Joint Legislative Committee on the State Education System, which developed a plan for school district reorganization across New York State, existed until 1947.
Source: New York State Archives finding aid for this collection.
Custodial History
According to the Joint Legislative Committee's final report, all files of the Rapp-Coudert investigations were turned over to the Division of State Police on March 5, 1947. The State Police borrowed and re-filed materials from the Rapp-Coudert files while the records were in its custody. The Rapp-Coudert files were originally accessioned as part of New York State Archives' Series A0795, Non-criminal investigation case files of the State Police, and filled boxes 65-84 of that series. In March 2009, the records were accessioned as a separate series (L0260).
Source: New York State Archives finding aid for this collection.
Based on an agreement with the New York State Archives (March 23, 2009), Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Archives funded the production of a microfilm copy of this collection. The New York State Archives received both the master negative and one positive copy. Tamiment Library retained one copy. The accession number associated with this collection is 2010.032.
Existence and Location of Originals
Original material is located at the New York State Archives, Albany, NY.
Other Finding Aids
The finding aid produced by the New York State Archives is available via the URL below:
http://iarchives.nysed.gov/xtf/view?docId=L0260.xml;query=;brand=default
Related Archival Materials
Many of Tamiment's archival collections contain materials associated with the Rapp-Coudert Committee. The following collections, in particular, concern individuals who are prominent within the Investigation Files: TAM 109, The Charles James Hendley Papers; TAM 179, The Morris Schappes Papers; TAM 254, The Henry Foner Papers.
The Reference Center for Marxist Studies Pamphlet Collection (PE043) contains two anti-committee pamphlets (Box 103, Folder 5):
Senator Coudert's Star Chamber: A Report on the Rapp-Coudert Committee: Private Hearings. The Committee for the Defense of Public Education, New York, 1941.
The Conspiracy Against the Schools. The Committee for the Defense of Public Education, New York. 1941.
The 1942 committee report referenced on the microfilm is available in the Tamiment Library:
Report of the Subcommittee of the Joint Legislative Committee to Investigate Procedures and Methods of Allocating State Moneys for Public School Purposes and Subversive Activities
Call Number LB2826.N7 A6 1942
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of investigation files generated by the Rapp-Coudert Committee as it probed suspected radical activities (mainly left-wing/Communist, some right-wing/Fascist and Nazi) in New York City public schools and colleges from 1940-1942. While the Committee cast its net broadly, the records reveal that it focused particular attention on New York City high schools, Brooklyn College, City College of New York and Hunter College. As it conducted investigations of students, faculty and administrators with suspected Communist or right-wing ties at these institutions, the Committee examined organizations such as the American Student Union, the Young Communist League, the Teachers Union and the College Teachers Union. It also devoted considerable attention to studying ethnic groups with ties to radical politics including German-Americans, Italian-Americans and Jewish-Americans, as well as foreign language teachers and others sympathetic to international causes (e.g., the labor movement.)
The bulk of the records include correspondence, interview notes, hearing transcripts, minutes, lists of various kinds, pamphlets, newspaper clippings and copies of publications compiled during the course of the investigations. Literature collected by the Committee ranges from flyers and student newspapers to leaflets and propaganda disseminated by the Communist Party. Themes such as Communism, anti-war sentiment and civil liberties dominate these publications. There are also references to the Spanish Civil War. Many files contain extensive Committee notes on individuals under investigation, and include witness testimony and notes on other persons with suspected ties to Communism. Notes are often annotated with page numbers, which in all likelihood correspond to the hearing transcripts where that information was captured. Much of the correspondence in this collection pertains to specific individuals of subversive activities or affiliations with left- or right-wing groups. Other letters to the Committee suggest witnesses for ongoing cases and provide "tips" on possible subversive behavior in New York City. Often, related documents such as newspaper clippings or other publications are attached to the letters.
Source: New York State Archives finding aid for this collection.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Researchers must use microfilm, the identifier is R-7860
Clippings (information artifacts); Pamphlets.; Notes.; Publications (documents); Legal documents.; Academic freedom -- New York (State) -- New York; Radicalism -- United States.; Anti-communist movements -- New York (State).; Italian Americans; Subversive activities -- United States.; Hearings (event); Teachers' unions -- New York (State) -- New York -- History -- 20th century.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Jews -- United States.; Minutes (administrative records); Interviews.; Correspondence.; Lists (document genres); Communism and education -- New York (State); New York (N.Y.).; Communist teachers -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (State) -- Politics and government.; College Teachers Union of New York City; Foner, Jack D.; Foner, Henry; Young Communist League of the U.S.; Foner, Philip Sheldon, 1910-1994; American Student Union; Foner, Moe, 1915-; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Brooklyn College; Dodd, Bella V., 1904-1969; Communist Party of the United States of America; Schappes, Morris U. (Morris Urman), 1907-2004; Hendley, Charles J.; Gideonse, Harry David, 1901-1985; College of the City of New York (1926-1961). City College; New York (State). Legislature. Joint Legislative Committee to Investigate the Educational System of the State of New York; New York State Archives
- Microfilm Reel List (with Cross-Reference to Original Box and Folder Locations), 1919-1953
  - Aronson, Dr. Moses (Assistant Professor, Philosophy, City College of New York): Interview (editorialized summary), 1940, 1947 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0001, Box-folder 1-RC1)
  - Abraham Lincoln High School: American Student Union (ASU) and NY Teachers Union, Touches on Anti-War and Anti-Fascist Activities, Spanish Civil War and Academic Freedom - Includes 'Findings', Student Complaints and a Number of Interview Summaries (many 'naming names'), 1936-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0011, Box-folder 1-RC2)
  - Ackley, John Kenneth (Registrar, CCNY; College Teachers Union Local 53 member): Includes Spanish Civil War, AFT, CCNY, Anti-Fascist Association, 1935-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0204, Box-folder 1-RC3)
  - Adams, Helen S., Dr. (Hunter College, American Federation of Teachers Official): Focus on Teachers Union, AFT, 1937-1938 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0288, Box-folder 1-RC4)
  - Alexander Hamilton High School: Focus on American Student Union (ASU), 1936-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0311, Box-folder 1-RC5)
  - Alpert, Jetta (Clerical Assistant, Townsend Harris High School), 1937-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0378, Box-folder 1-RC6)
  - American Civil Liberties Union: Three Booklets including A Gag on Teaching (1937), In the Shadow of War (1941) and Let Freedom Ring (1937), 1936-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0388, Box-folder 1-RC7)
  - American Committee for Friendship with the Soviet Union (broadsides), 1940 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0511, Box-folder 1-RC8)
  - American Friends of Spanish Democracy - Other Spanish Groups (broadsides), 1940 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0515, Box-folder 1-RC9)
  - American League Against War and Fascism (copies of articles), 1934-1935 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0519, Box-folder 1-RC10)
  - American Peace Mobilization, 1940-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0530, Box-folder 1-RC11)
  - American Student Union, High Schools: Includes Lengthy Report/Overview of ASU at NYC High Schools, Concerns Primarily Activities in 1930s, Mentions Young Communist League, 1941, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0619, Box-folder 1-RC12)
  - American Student Union, City College: Includes Handbills, Broadsides, ASU Recruitment Material; Flyer Announcing Speech Concerning Treatment of Jews in Germany and Anti-Nazi Underground, 1938-1941, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0691, Box-folder 1-RC13)
  - American Student Union, Columbia University: Includes Handbills, Broadsides, Pamphlets, 1940-1941, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0834, Box-folder 1-RC14)
  - American Student Union: Leaflets, Throwaways, Literature (including The Student Advocate of March 1938), 1938-1941, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-0861, Box-folder 1-RC15)
  - American Student Union: Official Action Regarding ASU - Includes Reports Such as Official Actions in Regard to ASU in City Schools and Colleges, also Circulars, Resolutions and Student Petitions (e.g., 1500 students protesting dismissal of Morris Schappes), 1935-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 1-1027, Box-folder 1-RC16)
  - American Student Union: Relations with Teachers Union, 1935-1940 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0001, Box-folder 1-RC17)
  - American Student Union: Includes List of "Communist" Teachers Lecturing ASU Groups; Materials from 1940 ASU Convention; and Chapter from Unfinished Book by Henry Linville - Chapter V The American Student Union, 1938-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0019, Box-folder 1-RC18)
  - American Student Union, Brooklyn College, Items 1-60: Includes Applications for Meeting Rooms, Interviews, Memos, Correspondence, Information Overviews Such as Summary of Facts re ASU at BC, ASU Charter of Student Rights and Responsibilities, 1935-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0216, Box-folder 1-RC19,1)
  - American Student Union, Brooklyn College, Items 61-201: Includes Applications for Meeting Rooms, Interviews, Broadsides, Handouts, List of Students Subpoenaed by the Committee, Pamphlets, Articles, 1938-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0399, Box-folder 1-RC19,2)
  - American Student Union, Hunter College, 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0591, Box-folder 1-RC20)
  - American Women Against Communism (AWAC) and Banta: Correspondence and Other Materials from AWAC and Edwin P. Banta (informer, former Communist, also associated with the German-American Bund), 1942 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0602, Box-folder 1-RC21)
  - American Youth Congress, 1940-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0635, Box-folder 1-RC22)
  - American Youth League: Includes List of Sponsors and Interview with National President - Winfield J. Demarest, 1940 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0671, Box-folder 1-RC23)
  - Amter, Israel: Private Hearing Exhibit (Communist candidate for Congressman-at-Large, district organizer for CPUSA and on the Executive Committee of the Workers School), 1933-1942 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0679, Box-folder 1-RC24)
  - Anderson, Paul B. (YMCA World Service Representative), [1941] (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0706, Box-folder 1-RC25)
  - Army Intelligence: Addresses and Telephone Numbers (Intelligence Section, District I, NYC), 1944 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0711, Box-folder 1-RC26)
  - Austin, Warren and Richard Warren: Letters Accusing them of Communist Party Membership (Warren Austin, English instructor at CCNY; Richard Warren, clerk in Registrar's Office CCNY), 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0716, Box-folder 1-RC27)
  - Attic Forum, 1940 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0722, Box-folder 1-RC28)
  - Balamuth, Lewis, 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0728, Box-folder 1-RC29)
  - Bardi, Gino (Candidate for Congress, American Labor Party), [1940] (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0734, Box-folder 1-RC30)
  - Bander, Ingram (Teacher of History at Bronx Vocational High School, terminated for testifying falsely about CP membership), 1938-1953 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0741, Box-folder 1-RC31)
  - Bernadette, Mercedes and Doris Bernadette (Teachers at Brooklyn College), 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0835, Box-folder 1-RC32)
  - Benjamin Franklin High School. Focus on Leonard Covello, Principal, 1936-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0846, Box-folder 1-RC33)
  - Bernstein, Saul (Biology instructor at CCNY): Includes Report of Board of Ed Trial Committee, 1936-1941, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0892, Box-folder 1-RC34)
  - Bloom, Solomon F. (History Department, Brooklyn College) Note: Portions of this folder not microfilmed, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 2-0934, Box-folder 1-RC35)
  - Braunlich, Arthur R. (ALP candidate 7th Assembly District 1940, tutor CCNY English Department), 1936-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0002, Box-folder 1-RC36)
  - Bridge, John (Chairman of CCNY Teachers Union,CCNY Classical Language Assistant Professor), [1940] (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0045, Box-folder 1-RC37)
  - Bronx High School of Science, 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0054, Box-folder 1-RC38)
  - Brooklyn Technical High School, [1941] (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0062, Box-folder 1-RC39)
  - Brooks, Alfred J. (PS 61 Bronx, Alleged CP member active in Teachers Union, aka A.G. Bosse), 1923-1927, 1940-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0084, Box-folder 1-RC40)
  - Buckvar, Oscar (CCNY Instructor, Government Department), 1943 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0131, Box-folder 1-RC41)
  - Burgun, Edwin B. (NYU-Washington Square College English Department; First President of TU Local 537; editor of Science & Society, a Marxist Quarterly): Includes Revolutionary Crisis: Fascism and War, 1933-1953 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0139, Box-folder 1-RC42)
  - Begun, Isidore (1939 Candidate for Bronx Councilman, active in the Teachers Union), 1933-1940 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0282, Box-folder 1-RC43)
  - Brooklyn College - Anti-Stalinist Radical Groups, 1938, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0309, Box-folder 1-RC45)
  - Brooklyn College: Calendar, Oct 1940-Dec 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0321, Box-folder 2-RC46)
  - Brooklyn College: Includes List of Sponsors for Teachers Union, Lists of Brooklyn College students, Lists of Faculty; Reports Such as Personalities of Brooklyn College Faculty from Dies Committee, Overview of Educational Investigation, Day-by-Day History of BC as Reflected in the Files of the NY Times and Brooklyn Eagle, Preliminary Outline of Evidence Concerning Subversive Activities at Brooklyn College e and Many Other Related Items., 1939-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0427, Box-folder 2-RC47)
  - Brooklyn College: Student Organizations, 1939-1942 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0621, Box-folder 2-RC48)
  - Brooklyn College: Chemistry Department, 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0677, Box-folder 2-RC49)
  - Brooklyn College: Karl Marx Society, 1939-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0683, Box-folder 2-RC50)
  - Brooklyn College: NYA Students, 1941, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0710, Box-folder 2-RC51)
  - Brooklyn College: Includes Interview with President Harry Gideonse (1943) and Copy of Student Activities Eligibility Regulations (1941), 1941-1943 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0728, Box-folder 2-RC52)
  - Brooklyn College: Peace Demonstrations (interview and report; memo "Walkout on War"), 1935-1940 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0760, Box-folder 2-RC53)
  - Brooklyn College: Student Publications (lists and notes on articles of interest), 1939-1941, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0775, Box-folder 2-RC54)
  - Brooklyn College: Students' Draft Status (called to military service or classified by local draft board), 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0860, Box-folder 2-RC55)
  - Cross Reference/Subject Guide, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0883, Box-folder 2-RC56)
  - Campbell, Harold G (Superintendent of Schools), 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0931, Box-folder 2-RC57)
  - Case, Meyer (Member of Teachers Non-Partisan Committee for the Election of Isidore Begun, Candidate for City Council 1937), undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0937, Box-folder 2-RC58)
  - Chakin, Al "Chick" (Wrestling Coach-CCNY, attended Peoples' Olympiad, Spain, 1936): Includes Flyer for Lecture on Experiences in Spain and Report on Conversation about Chakin (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0941, Box-folder 2-RC59)
  - Chein, Isadore: Photograph, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0945, Box-folder 2-RC60)
  - Childs, John L.: Material Related to Columbia University Local 537 AFT Conflict with Joint Board of NY City Teachers Union, 1935-1939, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0949, Box-folder 2-RC61)
  - Christopher Columbus High School: Peace Activities (John M. Laughran, Principal), 1936-1940, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0977, Box-folder 2-RC62)
  - Citron, Alice (PS 184, Manhattan, Member of Teachers Non-Partisan Committee for the Election of Isidore Begun), [1937] (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-0998, Box-folder 2-RC63)
  - Cohen, Joseph (Chairman Education Department, Brooklyn College: Interview Notes, 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-1002, Box-folder 2-RC64)
  - Cohen, Louis (New Utrecht High School, Member of Teachers Non-Partisan Committee for the Election of Isidore Begun), [1937] (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-1009, Box-folder 2-RC65)
  - Cohen, Morris (CCNY Instructor, Chemistry; 1939 Member of Teachers Union Executive Committee): Includes Charges and Letter of Suspension, 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-1013, Box-folder 2-RC66)
  - Cohen, Rosalyn (Brooklyn College): Involves Student-Diploma Issues, Suspected ASU or YCL Activities, 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-1025, Box-folder 2-RC67)
  - Collins, Harold (Teacher, Fort Hamilton High School), 1943 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 3-1029, Box-folder 2-RC68)
  - Columbia University: Includes Interviews with Potential Witnesses - Professors Edward Thorndike, Harry Hollingworth,Robert Woodworth, 1936-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0001, Box-folder 2-RC69)
  - Committee for Defense of Public Education: Includes "Report of Anti-Rapp-Coudert Committee" and Pamphlet "The Truth about the Schools", 1940-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0040, Box-folder 2-RC70)
  - Constitutional Educational League, Inc.: Includes Pamphlets "Communism in Schools" and "The Communist Fifth Column", 1942-1946 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0064, Box-folder 2-RC71)
  - Copstein, Seymour (Tutor of English, CCNY): Includes Report of Copstein Trial Committee as well as other Materials Related to Case Accusing Copstein of Membership in the Communist Party, 1935-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0104, Box-folder 2-RC72)
  - Cosenza, Mario Emilio (Brooklyn College): Includes Editorialized Summary of Interview, 1940 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0185, Box-folder 2-RC73)
  - Cross, Ephriam: Information Card, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0192, Box-folder 2-RC74)
  - Counts, George S.: Information Card, undated (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0195, Box-folder 2-RC75)
  - Custodial System: Interview Notes - R.J. Rigby, President, and Alexander Schwartz, Counsel of the School and Library Employees Local Union #74 (Building Service Employees of the AF of L), 1940 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0198, Box-folder 2-RC76)
  - Canning, Edna Moskowitz (Mrs. William M.): Notes of Interview, 1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0205, Box-folder 2-RC77)
  - Canning, William M.: Includes Interview Transcript, Portions of Testimony of Edna Canning, 1939-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0210, Box-folder 2-RC78)
  - "The Communist Party Election Platform" (not in a folder), 1936 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0250, Box-folder 2-No Folder)
  - City College: Lists of Young Communist League Members, Suspected Students; Interviews, Memos, Meeting Minutes, Notes from Testimony at Various Hearings; Documents Such as "Red Information", 1938-1941 (Reel R-7860, Reel frame 4-0259, Box-folder 2-RC79)